A Guide to the Greensville County (Va.) Judgments, 1782-1910
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Greensville County (Va.) Judgments, 1782-1910
The Library of Virginia
0007613767, 0007843085-0007843092, 0007843099, 0007843116
4.5 cu. ft. (10 boxes)
Greensville County (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Judgments, 1790-1900 that were transferred in accession 53810 under the title “Greensville County Dead Papers” and in adjacent boxes have undergone minimal processing. The remaining judgments from this locality are still unprocessed and need review prior to use by researchers. All records remain tri-folded or in original bundles and may be fragile. Contact Archives Research services for availability.
Acquisition Information
These records came to the Library of Virginia in a 2009 transfer of court papers from Greensville County under accession number 44478 and in a 2023 transfer of court papers from Greensville County under accession number 53810.
Historical Information
Locality History: Greensville County was named either for Revolutionary War general Nathanael Greene, commanding general of the Continental army in the South during part of the Revolutionary War, or for Sir Richard Grenville, leader of the Roanoke Island settlement of 1585. The county was formed from Brunswick County on 28 November 1780.
Scope and Content
Judgments were civil cases in which justice was administered on the strictly formulated rules of common law. The majority of cases in this record group relate to matters of debt.
Records in this series have not been fully processed and indexed, but the 1790-1900 Judgments that were transferred in accession 53810 under the title “Greensville County Dead Papers” and in adjacent boxes have undergone standard minimal processing. minimal processing has allowed for the documentation of specific record types and various trends found in this set of records.
Judgments, 1829-1900 that have undergone minimal processing consist of the following record types: pleas of trespass; capias; writs of mittimus; scifas (scire facias); complete judgments; executions; pleas of debt; pleas of damage; narratios; delivery bonds; attachment bonds; appeal bonds; attachments; declarations; summons re: judgments; subpoenas re: judgments; fifas (fieri facias); casas (capias as satisfaciendum); accounts; declaration bonds; railroad land condemnations; counter/new security re: fiduciary matters; unlawful detainer; writs of ad quod damnum; indemnity bonds; replevy bonds.
Significant materials in the minimally processed records include several cases that discuss the sale of enslaved people as well as an 1833 case pertaining to a schoolteacher who was accused of abusing his students.
The remaining judgments accessioned under the number 53810 and all judgments accessioned under the number 44478 are still unprocessed and are interfiled with other unprocessed court records transferred from Greensville County.
Arrangement
Judgments, 1790-1900 which have undergone minimal processing are loosely arranged chronologically. All other judgments remain unprocessed.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Greensville County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
Contents List
- Judgments, 1790-1900, 2.25 cubic feet (5 boxes)
  Loosely arranged chronologically.
  - Judgments, 1790-1830
  - Judgments, 1830-1833
  - Judgments, 1833-1837
  - Judgments, 1837-1844
  - Judgments, 1844-1900
- Judgments, 1782-1910, 2.25 cubic feet (5 boxes)
  Interfiled with other unprocessed material for Greensville County.
  - Judgments, 1782-1910
  - Judgments; Tax & Fiscal; Criminal, 1860-1869
  - Criminal; Judgements; Chancery Causes, 1869-1872
  - Court Papers; Judgments, 1891-1893
  - Judgments, 1867-1892